Yeah.
Oh. We're going to find a question that's for you now.
We'll pass you some suggestions, Todd.
Okay.
Morning, Grant. It's great to have you back, and Andrew.
Good.
And
if you want to give a bit of a preamble and-
Sure. Sure
... and then we'll just have a pretty relaxed Q&A.
So I thought I could kick off with just a thumbnail reflection on
the year to June.
I've made some commitments to the House, and you've given me the opportunity to
reflect back on progress, and so that'll be very short.
And then spend a bit of time talking about, from our
office's perspective, how we see the context within which the public
service is operating and some of the change and therefore some of the
inherent risks that come with that.
So yeah, off the back of that, a conversation about how we
can enable scrutiny by Parliament in that environment, I think would be
really helpful for us to go back and reflect on that in building up our
future work program. So quickly,
on the performance for the year ended
June '26.
We still have an annoying tail of basic statutory audit arrears,
but we're making progress.
And it is still those very small entities in some schools, some
of which have
been wound up, and so it's a thing which I want to draw an
end to, is chasing former boards of trustees to figure out who might
be able to actually sign on behalf of the entity so that I can sign an audit
report. So we're getting more granular in terms of understanding
what's in that tail, which gives me confidence we're making progress.
If we look at the discretionary work program,
we did eight pieces of performance audit work in the 12 months,
and three follow-ups. There's probably four themes coming out of that
discretionary work, which I'll just whip through now.
But
there's opportunities across those eight for agencies to better use the
data they have in front of them to target their services.
And we can get into that later if the committee are interested.
We have lots of meetings across ecosystems or sectors,
but those meetings, in our view, are not being informed with joined-up information
that enables concentrated discussion on the things those entities can do
better together.
And so the inquiry work that this committee led,
which we're awaiting on government response for, the
notion of having a kind of framing of sectoral reporting, we
think is going to be really important to elevating some of that focus in
those cross-agency meetings onto topics
that matter.
Strategic financial management capability, I think we've spoken to the committee
previously about that.
We've joined up with Treasury and PSC.
It's an area of focus for the three of us.
And there are some good things PSC in particular are leading in that
space. But
given everything else that's going on, we need the capability quickly in order to
make some safe decisions around trade-offs going forward.
And sharing of data
by agencies and better management, better measurement
of and evaluation of the effectiveness of programs.
SIA is doing some really good thinking and some really good work, but it's
tiny in the scheme of
social sector spend. So while we're encouraged by some of the things we're
seeing in SIA, we're turning our minds to, well, how do we
work with them in a way that provokes uptake of that thinking
more quickly by more agencies?
In terms of the context, it's trite to say
change
is kind of
a feature. We've got machinery of government ambitions which
are at a different scale than we've seen for a very long time in this country
or in fact, ever. We've got layers of reform
impacting local government.
There's a real ambition to leverage the investment in
data and AI technologies.
There's a move to larger entities, a move to
centralize things inside the central agencies like the
GDDA.
We don't have views whether these are the right or wrong things.
We just think
change creates a unique set of inherent risks that we
want to make sure that we're across and we're advising Parliament
in the best way possible
to enable you to be across them.
So at
one level, it's just change. But if I pick on, not pick on local
government, but
some of the water reform, the leg has happened, but now we've got
entities trying to deal with the individual contexts they're operating in.
We've got the same people involved in amalgamation.
And so it's the layering that is quite different to what we've seen
in a part of our public service system, which
has never had the best
capabilities
that the system has available to it.
So the stretch on that sector in particular is something that we're
acutely mindful of. And with the long-term planning around
about to kick off,
we're trying to be careful to make sure our
assurance involvement is not distracting or slowing things
down. But equally,
the legislation requires us to audit, and audit's done to a standard.
So we're trying to be early and do all those good things, but the
absorptive capacity in that sector in particular is something that really does
get me kind of thinking, are we
doing enough to support them?
Sorry, but
it's just the
other things on my daily sheet of what's
really driving my attention at the moment.
Large scale change, one thing we know from looking backwards is,
there's inherent risks that you see a performance dip as you
distract the workforce from delivering the services that New Zealanders need them
to keep delivering.
At the same time, we've
said to the committee previously, we don't believe the performance frameworks that
are across the public service sufficiently
enable a real lens into what's actually going on under the hood.
So are they transparent enough so you know whether or
not that uncertainty is actually creating a
degradation of service delivery or not?
So that's one thing we are spending some time on, and we'll
try and integrate into our briefings to various committees,
to make sure if we're seeing degradation of service,
we're bringing that to the attention of the House.
Absorptive capacity is something that we're really
mindful of.
Centralization is a thing.
We've all of an age where we've seen this, and I'm
not saying it's a right or wrong model,
but actually it comes with a whole bunch of inherent
challenges, particularly around the risk of losing a
local voice.
And so the way in which the center remains connected
to
the coalface where services are delivered becomes increasingly
important because your ability to rely on those regional
local relationships as a good source of intelligence,
you need to think differently about how the center's getting access
to those more real time
pieces of information that allow you to understand where you might need to
course-correct.
I'm telling you things you already know, but I guess
what I'm trying to signal is, these are the things that I want my teams
to be very mindful of in preparing the briefings for all committees, so
that
if everything's going fine and these inherent risk characteristics are being taken
account of, I'll be the happiest man alive.
But
we just need to make sure that we've got our eyes on them.
Grant, do you mind if I kick off with a question?
Go ahead. Mm-hmm.
Firstly, I really like the plan. I thought it was really coherent and easy to
follow along, given the complexity of government.
Good.
So kudos to you and the team.
I did wonder, through the... And I know you gave examples like on
education, like school learner, the budgets for education, reaching
school learner objectives and that sort of stuff.
Is that a bit of a hint of the work we did on the performance reporting
stuff that's starting to try and link outcomes clearer to
budgets?
Yep. I'm unashamedly
trying to leverage that great inquiry work,
and to, I guess, not wait for the systemic changes which
may or may not happen, but actually say, well...
I don't want to put words in the committee's mouth, but I think it was a pretty
united conclusion in that report that we could do better, and
that here are some examples of areas where we can do better.
So we're using that to-
I thought that was-
Yeah
... excellent, actually, to link government policy of the day-
... to actually financials. Well done.
Question on 17 under infrastructure.
You talked about infrastructure and obviously the challenges that we've had as a
country. Good at spending money on it, not so good at bang for buck, and
you identify that around the RCD piece.
Yeah.
You talked about maybe, well, you're going to track a large
spend and track that through, but also you talked about incentives for public
organizations to deliver better, and I just wondered if you could unpack that a
bit. What would those incentives look like?
I don't want to attribute, but
some of our programs have been very
slow to get to spend, if we're honest.
They're approved, but the delay, and as a
nation, we draw debt down from the capital markets,
and we incur interest costs holding that debt before the thing gets
underway. And so
should there be, and we don't have views on what the arrangements are, but
in talking to Treasury, are there ways in which
organizations that are causing the delay can
effectively be exposed to some of those consequences of the
delay?
There's a whole range of instruments.
You could sheet the interest cost home to the project, for example, if you want to
be blunt about it. But that's not for us to design, but
we do want to understand, are the incentives
not sufficiently
creating the right tension for people to get on with it?
Is that similar to what I know some councils have used with,
I'm trying to think the entities, where it's not a cost share, but there's an
incentive on the agency. If they can save money through their
spend, it's shared with the organization.
Is that similar or-
Yeah. Risk sharing or upside sharing
arrangements are pretty standard features of
commercial contracting situations.
So we just want, through our work, to
explore whether or not those arrangements have a role to play
in
getting bang for buck through these-
Yeah, sure
... large projects.
Megan.
Sorry.
Thank you. I think that debt spending track is a really interesting
part, and the idea of sheeting those interest costs to the
project.
In terms of, do you have any sense
across a particular- Agency, have you done any
looking at what that might actually look like in terms
of shifting costs or saving costs?
We haven't yet, but-
Right
... yeah.
And,
so a really good incentive. No agency's going to want to carry the
increased interest costs on it.
Is there a kind of a parallel carrot that you could put in place
there as well
to incentivize
better kind of
faster moving on projects? Because obviously, there's going to have applications
for the debt spending track there too.
Yeah.
There will be a range of positive incentives-
Yeah
... rather than whacking them with costs that can be-
... built into it. And again, we're interested in how
the processes that those spending entities are
required to work themselves through.
Yeah.
One of them could, and sorry, this is me just responding.
This is not a position of the office.
But
there is lots of
reflection on whether we've got the business case
model right.
Yeah.
And the idea that some
relief from some of the very
detail heavy
aspects, if you're an accredited organization with a track record of...
There are ways in which you can give relief through-
Okay
... stage gating.
Sorry, I'm just trying to-
No, that's really interesting. Thank you.
I've got Todd and then Deborah.
Oh, thanks. Thanks for being here.
I'm just interested, actually, in the topic around Crown entity monitoring.
I know it looks, well, obviously you did some work a few years ago.
Yeah.
But keen just to get your thoughts on where you see that going, because I think
this is really important because,
yeah, obviously
you've got some different departments, and I'm just thinking of like DIA, say,
monitoring FENS, for example.
Yeah.
And some people might say that that hasn't been as effective as it could have been.
But I'm just keen to, yeah, get your initial thoughts.
Have you identified particular monitoring entities you want to look
at, or if that's still under development, and yeah, because this is pretty
important because often they're probably maybe not doing it quite the-
Yeah
... job that ministers need.
It's still in development, but if I look at some
characteristics that I am very interested in, it's where we have
a relatively small ministry or department
monitoring a very large Crown entity.
I think that creates a particular type of
power relationship which I wonder
how the monitoring agency kind of works in that context.
And I'm also interested,
and these are formulative thoughts so hopefully the committee
appreciate I'm just being open about-
Yeah
... our thinking.
Is there a way in which the monitoring function can move from
being a passive recipient of
ex-post reporting from the agency, putting that into a briefing note,
and to a relationship they have with the entity they are monitoring,
which is better understanding of context and strategic
direction, and actually can have the tension in
the relationship. But
they're effectively like an equity analyst, so they
are sufficiently
senior and experienced that they can make a
contribution back to the entity they are monitoring.
Not to get in the way of their independence, but
I'm very keen to explore whether that
model
actually could work for the better aggregate performance of the
ministry they're embedded in and the Crown entity.
And I've road tested that with some of the central agencies, and we think
there's ground to explore there. And I do know that
the central agencies are actually working with some of the monitoring
departments at the moment
to think differently about the model, to think differently about the type of
capability you put into your monitoring teams.
Yeah.
And there's no statutory barrier to them doing it in a different way.
So I mean, what you're saying seems to make perfect sense to
me, and it actually, I think, is what's needed because I think, yeah, as you said,
at the moment, it's quite a passive relationship and we probably actually need to
be a much more active monitor and
identify issues earlier.
Would that be...?
Yeah. And
to be honest, when we're road testing these ideas, there's no resistance to
the notion it could be improved, either by the departments who have
monitoring responsibilities or the agencies they're monitoring.
And hopefully we've got a contribution to make to the how.
And sorry, just one last quick last one.
Obviously, from your previous experience, because obviously relatively
new, you've been in the role-
Yeah
... not for a little while, but did you see, is that the kind of the way
monitoring functions are moving in, say, even in the private sector or?
Yeah. Well, if I look at the role, for example, a corporate
treasury sitting at the heart of a multinational-
Yeah
... network in terms of
its influence on capital allocation decisions made by autonomous
subsidiaries.
I'm not saying that model is directly transferable, but it does-
I mean-
... seem to galvanize some focus on
some strategic conversations as opposed to a passive kind of...
Yeah.
Very good.
Thank you.
Thank you. Dr. Deborah.
Actually, that kind of follows on from this because as
I was listening to how you're describing the work you're doing, it's
within that monitoring space and how do we get-
Agencies to do better and-
Mm
... so then who else does that work?
And of course, Treasury does it in various units within things.
So it's quite a complex landscape of who's doing the monitoring-
Mm
... and the reporting back, and there's the
reporting back to us obviously, and reporting back to the agencies.
But then Treasury's got a much more internalized role in that as well.
So it's a-
Well,
I do think this is a moment in time where machinery of
government change is being contemplated.
Yeah.
And so how you best design the
system to monitor the delivery by those large Crown
entities, yeah, I think it's a really
timely question to be posed as we're looking
at
how agencies are pulled together potentially, and where
responsibilities sit. And is the having monitoring
activity happening in a range of places across the system, the
right model?
Who knows?
Yeah. I guess one of the things that's got me, just been thinking about
it as we've been sitting here because you were talking about change and
the way that after you go through
change, structural change or whatever, you typically get a drop-off in performance,
which is worth us being aware of because
doesn't mean we shouldn't change stuff, it just means you've got to have a bit of
an understanding of the context.
But I was thinking too, and this links back to some of the stuff we were worrying
about with debt management track.
If we do the monitoring wrong, we make public servants risk
averse.
And if we're too
light touched, they take unnecessary risks.
But if we're too heavy-handed,
they won't take any risks at all. And I
doubt there's even a sweet spot. There might be a range where it's kind of-
Yeah
... get the level of monitoring and reporting about right.
Have you been thinking that through?
Yeah, and I think the most effective
monitoring agencies have reached a meeting of
minds with the entities they're monitoring around things they're going to be
tight on.
Yeah
And things that they're going to be more permissive around or...
And I think the earlier in the relationship they can come to
that meeting of minds, the better off and the
better the monitoring works because
the agency knows the things that are going to be under the microscope.
And so almost if the
only thing the monitoring entity does is reach that agreement, I think you'll see
the downstream change in behaviors that would be in the interests of both
parties.
Mm.
Yes.
But it's not a quick or easy process, so we
can't...
We've talked about this so much just in terms of the length of
governments and things like that, and the pressure for us to deliver
quick results. But we know that if we put that pressure on
our
state capacity, then we get mistakes.
But if we don't make some mistakes, then we don't make any...
It's
a complicated space.
Yep. And the maturity
of the accountability discussions kind of send pretty
significant signals back into the public service about
striking that balance, right? So if every mistake is met with the same
reaction,
you'll get changes in behavior, be they positive or
negative, depending on the proportionality of the reaction
to the situation.
Yeah. Just going to go to Dr. Dave Harrison.
Yeah. I'm going to carry on with Todd and Deborah's
line of thought here, because we're dealing with the Audit Office here, and when
people think audit, they think financial.
And yet we're moving to an outcomes-based performance measurement
approach.
And we're also talking about monitoring.
So we can monitor and see that the financials are fine.
The problem is we may be actually doing the wrong things.
The activities may not be correct, and we're not heading towards the outcomes we
want to achieve. So I guess that's my question is, how do we
actually think about it in terms of monitoring,
to broaden that kind of thought process or get that
inculcated into the monitoring agencies and so on?
Yeah, I think it's around saying that you are monitoring a
relationship around results rather than
controllables.
And one of the themes which I've probably brushed over coming out of the
work we've done this last 12 months is just
the absence of evaluative
work to enable agencies. We've pointed
out that they don't report on impacts or results or
outcomes. If you think, well, what
enables them to do that, it is spending time and
resource evaluating the effectiveness of the programs you
run. And
that
it's not for me to tell agencies where they should spend money, but it
seems to be a critical inhibitor to the quality of
performance reporting that we've
all spent lots of time
on. I'd have to look because there's something on here-
No, there was just someone waving at me. Sorry.
Oh, okay.
One of my colleagues giving a to-er.
I'm with Ryan. We got a long way down that whole performance
measurement and outcome
work, which I think is fabulous.
Yep.
Now we're at the crunchy bit, aren't we, as to how do we actually make-
Well, I understand some of my team are in front of the committee later in
August-
End of the month, yeah
... to try and have a conversation about, well, irrespective, well,
we will have the government response by then, but kind of irrespective of the
response to the inquiry's final report, here are
some things that we want your views on because they are the ways in which
we intend to work with committees
to enhance scrutiny. And it's directly
related to shifting our focus. And we've got
to be careful. And I'm a chartered accountant, so
it's not a move away from-
No, exactly
... financial integrity, right? It's an and.
Absolutely.
Yeah. That's a good place to probably wrap up. But thank you very much, gentlemen.
Thank you.
Andrew, your colleague, are you going to leave here with any burning regrets you
didn't say anything? Just want to give you- No.
They'll give me feedback on the way back to the office.
Very good. Thanks for your time.
Thank you.
See you on the other side of the election.
Yeah. Good luck.
Thank you.
94 days to go.
Not that you're counting, Des.
82 days to go to Advanced-
Yes, that's right